Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is lamed
ל', Lamed, thirty.
And it is 43 days in the omer עומר. Omer. 43. I
said
43. Oh, I thought you said 43.
Anyway, we pick up from the gemara גמרא Gemara at the bottom
of kaf tet amud bet כ"ט עמוד ב', Kaf Tet Amud Bet,
right after the mishnah משנה. Mishnah. So the mishnah משנה Mishnah gave
the basic principles of piggul פיגול. Piggul. We are finally in the
heart of piggul פיגול. Piggul. It has to be a thought during
one of the avodot עבודות avodot of the blood: shechitah שחיטה, shechitah,
kabalah קבלה, kabalah, holachah הולכה, holachah, or zerikah זריקה. zerikah. And it
has to be a thought about one of the achilot אכילות, achilot,
either the achilat ha-dam אכילת הדם achilat ha-dam she-be-ha-ra'uy lo הראוי לו
ha-ra'uy lo or the achilat mizbeach אכילת מזבח achilat mizbeach of the
dam דם dam or of the emurim אימורים emurim to do it
at the wrong time. If it's the wrong place, then it's pasul
פסול pasul but it's not piggul פיגול. Piggul. And then you have
the debate in the mishnah משנה Mishnah
between
the tanna kamma תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda where the tanna kamma תנא קמא Tanna Kamma felt that
a bad thought of chutz li-mkomo חוץ למקומו chutz li-mkomo or shelo
lishmo שלא לשמה shelo lishmo by a chatas חטאת chatas stopped the
thing from being piggul פיגול Piggul even if the bad thought came
after the piggul פיגול Piggul thought, whereas rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda said no, it's all defined by the first thought. If first
you had the other bad thought, then it's already pasul פסול, pasul,
can't become piggul פיגול. Piggul. But if first you had the piggul
פיגול Piggul thought, then the bad thought that comes afterwards cannot invalidate
its piggul פיגול Piggul status. Okay, so that was the debate. So
let's take a look at the gemara גמרא. Gemara. Amar ilfa אמר
אילפא, Amar Ilfa, said Ilfa, three lines from the, four lines on
the bottom of kaf tet amud bet כ"ט עמוד ב'. Kaf Tet
Amud Bet. Amar ilfa machloket bi-shtei avodot אמר אילפא מחלוקת בשתי עבודות.
Amar Ilfa machloket bi-shtei avodot. The debate of rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda and the rabbanan רבנן Rabbanan and the chachamim חכמים Chachamim
is you have piggul פיגול Piggul thought by shechitah שחיטה shechitah and
chutz li-mkomo חוץ למקומו chutz li-mkomo thought by zerikah זריקה zerikah let's
say, or holachah הולכה, holachah, or the reverse. And then the question
is, does it go by the first thought, rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה,
Rebbe Yehuda, that defines its identity, or any pasul פסול pasul thought
stops it from being piggul פיגול? Piggul? That's the debate. Aval be-avodah
achat divrei ha-kol eiruv machshavot havei אבל בעבודה אחת דברי הכל עירוב
מחשבות הוי. Aval be-avodah achat divrei ha-kol eiruv machshavot havei.
But if during the shechitah שחיטה shechitah you were thinking like actually
like the end of the mishnah משנה Mishnah actually sounds like, I'm
going to eat a kezayit כזית kezayit in the wrong place and
a kezayit כזית kezayit in the wrong time, or let's say you
are thinking not even two separate kezayisim כזיתים, kezayisim, when you're doing
the shechitah שחיטה shechitah you're thinking I'm going to eat a kezayit
כזית kezayit in the wrong place and in the wrong time or
something like that, anyway, if you have both of those thoughts during
one avodah עבודה, avodah, even rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda agrees
that that invalidates the korban קרבן. korban. Okay, his only point is
that if it first becomes piggul פיגול, Piggul, I mean you know
that that stops the korban קרבן korban from being piggul פיגול. Piggul.
His only point is that if it first becomes piggul פיגול Piggul
then another bad thought can't interfere with its piggul פיגול Piggul status.
Okay, that's what he says. Rabbi yochanan amar af be-avodah achat machloket
רבי יוחנן אמר אף בעבודה אחת מחלוקת. Rabbi Yochanan amar af be-avodah
achat machloket. No,
even if it's during the same avodah עבודה, avodah, okay, it is
a debate. And actually I think I slightly misstated avodah achat עבודה
אחת avodah achat because I'm jumping to some cases later in the
gemara גמרא. Gemara. The case of like avodah achat עבודה אחת avodah
achat is while you still have an order for what you're saying
the things but you do it during one avodah עבודה. avodah. So
as you're shachting שוחט shachting you're saying I am intending to eat
this, you know, chutz li-zmano חוץ לזמנו chutz li-zmano and now I'm
intending to eat it chutz li-mkomo חוץ למקומו. chutz li-mkomo. You have
both of those thoughts, you know, maybe one follows the next but
they're all during one avodah עבודה. avodah. So ilfa אילפא Ilfa says
that okay, since it's all during one avodah עבודה avodah it prevents
it from being piggul פיגול. Piggul. And rabbi yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says as long as the first thought was about piggul פיגול,
Piggul, even if the next thought was about chutz li-mkomo חוץ למקומו
chutz li-mkomo and even if it's during one avodah עבודה, avodah, then
even in that case rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would say
it's already piggul פיגול, Piggul, you can't stop it from being piggul
פיגול. Piggul. Okay, now bishlama le-ilfa mi-reisha bi-shtei avodot seifa nami bi-shtei
avodot בשלמא לאילפא מדרישא בשתי עבודות סיפא נמי בשתי
עבודות. bishlama le-Ilfa mi-reisha bi-shtei avodot seifa nami bi-shtei avodot. Since the
first case in the mishnah משנה, Mishnah, right because remember the first
case that the mishnah משנה Mishnah discussed was explicitly, you do the
shechitah שחיטה shechitah with this thought, you do the holachah kabalah הולכה
קבלה holachah kabalah blah blah blah blah blah with the other thought.
So that's a clear case of two separate avodot עבודות. avodot. Okay,
but then the second part of the mishnah משנה, Mishnah, right, when
the mishnah משנה Mishnah got to the section where it's going to
quote rebbe yehuda's רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda's debate, if you remember it
says this is like
okay, four lines down in the wide lines from where we're reading,
if you see le-chol kezayit ba-chutz kezayit li-machar לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית
למחר. le-chol kezayit ba-chutz kezayit li-machar.
So that's the question. Right, when let's finally erase this pasuk פסוק.
pasuk. Whole pasuk פסוק pasuk which we learned
all the halachos הלכות halachos
of piggul
פיגול. Piggul.
Anyway. That's going to be on the final.
I know. Well, I hope you got it in your notes.
I do.
It's in these notes too. Okay, excellent.
So if okay, so the first part of the mishnah משנה Mishnah
was, you know, you have shechitah שחיטה, shechitah, kabalah קבלה, kabalah, holachah
הולכה, holachah, zerikah זריקה. zerikah. So the first part of the mishnah
משנה Mishnah had the case where for example you did this chutz
li-zmano חוץ לזמנו chutz li-zmano
and then you did this, you know, whatever, let's say over here
chutz li-mkomo חוץ למקומו. chutz li-mkomo. Okay,
and it's clear that that would be a case that rebbe yehuda
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would debate. You've already established it as piggul
פיגול, Piggul, so chachamim חכמים Chachamim say that stops it as piggul
פיגול Piggul and rebbe yehuda רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says no, it's
too bad, it's already piggul פיגול. Piggul. The next part of the
משנה Mishnah said, that was the first part of the משנה. Mishnah.
The next part of the משנה Mishnah just said כזית למחר k'zayis
l'machar and
כזית בחוץ, k'zayis bachutz,
right? That was the next part of the משנה. Mishnah. And then
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda debated and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said that
wouldn't be פיגול pigul and the חכמים Chachamim said it would be
פיגול, pigul, right? Same idea. Because this is this is חוץ מזמנו,
chutz mizmano, then it's חוץ ממקומו, chutz mimkomo, so the חכמים Chachamim
said that would be פיגול, pigul, it would not be פיגול, pigul,
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it already is פיגול, pigul, you
don't stop it from being פיגול. pigul. So the question was, in
this case, what is this? Is all this what you're thinking about
while you're doing שחיטה? Shechita?
And that's עבודה אחת, avoda achas, that's what אילפא Ilfa says, while
you're doing שחיטה, Shechita, okay wait no, did I get that wrong?
No, אילפא Ilfa says no, I'm sorry, אילפא Ilfa says if it's
during one עבודה, avoda, okay, then even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
it's not פיגול. pigul. Okay, so אילפא Ilfa says that this case
where they're debating this parallels the case above. This is what you're
thinking while you're doing שחיטה Shechita and this is while you're doing
זריקה. Zerika. Okay, and that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's
already פיגול. pigul. But if you're thinking all of this while you're
doing שחיטה, Shechita, then even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say it's
not פיגול. pigul. Whereas רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right, it's רבי יוחנן?
Rabbi Yochanan? Whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, you're thinking all
of this while you're doing שחיטה, Shechita, and even so רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says since this came first, it's already פיגול pigul and
you can't ruin it with that thought. Okay, so this is אילפא's
Ilfa version of it, אילפא Ilfa says it's that's how it was,
and רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan version of it is that it's all
during שחיטה Shechita
or whatever it is,
whatever, but we'll just use that as an example. Okay, and that's
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
Yes.
So okay, so just trying to, let me just go back to
the base for a second. So if for פיגול, pigul, even if
I don't eat it on the third day, you know, you eat
it like that day, it's still כרת kares because there was the
פיגול pigul thought. Right. So what I'm trying to understand is, like,
so the כהן, Kohein, there's the שחיטה, Shechita, right? And let's say
then I'm the בעל, ba'al, I know nothing, and then I eat
it, and it's a פיגול pigul קרבן, korban, so I'm כרת. kares.
Right, so you'd be like אונס ones or something.
So do I have to actually bring an atonement?
No, you'd be like, well presumably you'd be an אונס, ones, but
it's a good question. Like because it's like חלב ועריות, chelev ve'arayos,
but presumably, but that's the... anyway there's no מתעסק mis'asek by חלב
ועריות, chelev ve'arayos, but this is this is an אונס ones case.
It's it's an interesting question.
Like you totally were to... presumably he didn't... I understand, I understand,
I understand. I mean, no, I think presumably no, מתעסק mis'asek is...
anyway yeah, I think you're an אונס, ones, you're פטור. patur. I
mean, you know, you had no reason to know, he didn't tell
you, you should have assumed it was
kosher.
But they still bring another קרבן? korban?
Oh yeah, you have to bring another קרבן, korban, that has nothing
to do with eating the meat. Yeah, I know. Yeah, and then
that has to do with whether the כהן Kohein has a has
a נזק nezek liability, which is discussed in like a משנה Mishnah
in גיטין. Gittin. Okay.
Rabbi, is there a discussion about when the כהן Kohein realizes that
he's had this thought?
No, what do you mean? Like if he never realizes, then everybody
is an אונס... ones... well, he's an אונס ones from his thought,
but... Exactly. It's never discovered.
But I mean, if he realizes it, like you know, after the
whole thing's done, then it goes into effect.
Right, well it's gone into effect, but now everybody realizes it's gone
into effect, right. Okay, so אמר אילפא מחלוקת בשתי עבודות. Amar Ilfa
machlokes bishtei avodos. So this debate in this part of the משנה
Mishnah between whether this is פיגול pigul or not, אילפא Ilfa says
it's talking about like the first part, שתי עבודות, shtei avodos, okay,
and therefore and therefore what do you call it, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says it was already established as פיגול pigul and you can't
change it. אבל בעבודה אחת דברי הכל אינו פיגול, Aval be'avoda achas
divrei hakol eino pigul, it was all during שחיטה, Shechita, even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say it doesn't get to be פיגול. pigul.
רבי יוחנן אמר אף בעבודה אחת מחלוקת. Rabbi Yochanan amar af be'avoda
achas machlokes. No, even there רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it gets
to be פיגול. pigul. בשלמא לאילפא היינו דתני זה הכלל, Bishelama le'Ilfa
haynu deteni zeh haklal, סיפא נמי בשתי עבודות. seifa nami bishtei avodos.
So
okay, by אילפא Ilfa it parallels the case above. Of course you
could say but then it's repetitive, why do you need it? So
רש״י Rashi says you need it to tell you the whole thing
about חצי זית וחצי זית chatzi zayis ve'chatzi zayis and so on.
Okay, but according to אילפא Ilfa at least it's the same as
the case above and they're talking about separate עבודות. avodos. אלא לרבי
יוחנן רישא בשתי עבודות וסיפא בעבודה אחת? Ella le'Rabbi Yochanan reisha bishtei
avodos ve'seifa be'avoda achas?
How is it that we go from here talking about separate thoughts
during separate עבודות avodos and here we talk about having the whole
thought during the one עבודה? avoda? ואמר אין, Ve'amar in, yeah, רישא
בשתי עבודות וסיפא בין בעבודה אחת בין בשתי עבודות. reisha bishtei avodos
ve'seifa bein be'avoda achas bein bishtei avodos. Actually פשט pshat of the
משנה Mishnah I think reads better like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's
funny that the גמרא Gemara had that question, exactly because we've already
discussed about different thoughts during two different עבודות, avodos, now we're talking
about you had this thought presumably during one עבודה, avoda, right? and
a כזית kezayit to do that and a כזית kezayit to do
that. Anyway, so that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says and he
says even here, even during one עבודה, avoda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say it already gets established as פיגול, pigul, the other thing
doesn't interfere. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue, don't let
the two dots you know
deceive you. תנן: Tenan: אמר רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yehuda זה הכלל
zeh haklal אם מחשבת הזמן קדמה למחשבת המקום פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת.
im machshaves hazman kadma lemachshaves hamakom pigul vechayavin alav kares. If this
thought time about time comes first, it's פיגול pigul and then it
doesn't
change and חייבין עליו כרת. chayavin alav kares. בשלמא לרבי יוחנן היינו
דתני זה הכלל, Bishelama le'Rabbi Yochanan haynu deteni zeh haklal, because זה
הכלל zeh haklal means it's a broad category, whether it comes in
a one עבודה avoda and the thing comes as a later עבודה,
avoda, it's already, you know, it goes by the first thought, or
whether it's already
פיגול. pigul. stopped being it. אלא איפכא מאי זה הכלל *Ella Ipcha
mai zeh haklal*? What does the זה הכלל *zeh haklal* mean since
it's only about a case of two עבודות avodot. *avodot*? קשיא טאקע
*Kashya takka*. That's a problem. Okay, תנן התם *Tnan hatam*. We taught
over there in תמורה tmura *Temurah*. הרי זה תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים
tmuras olah
tmuras shelamim, *Harei zeh tmurat olah tmurat shelamim*. So now we're going
to have a parallel question about, well possibly parallel, about if you
say two things, you know, do you look at them as a
package or do you look at them as the first thing? Because
what's the real issue? תפוס לשון אחרון *Tfos lashon acharon*? That's what
it says it's going to be in the what is the case
if we're talking about during one. Really, if איפכא *Ipcha* and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan* debating if you say this during one
עבודה avoda *avodah*. That איפכא *Ipcha* says we wrap it all up
as a package and it doesn't first get to be פיגול pigul
*pigul* if it's all during one עבודה avoda *avodah*, even for רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, right? And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi
Yochanan* says no, even for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, even
if it's all during one עבודה avoda? *avodah*, we divide up the
two, it's two stages. Okay, so that's really the question. The question
is within רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* that says if it's
clearly A and then B, A already established it. When you do
it during one עבודה avoda *avodah*, do we look at it as
they're both at the same time or do we look at it
as sequential? So that is going to be something that we can
compare this to. Okay, when you look at like one statement during
one time, do you look at it as A and then B
or do you look at it as a package? If it's a
package, it's not פיגול pigul *pigul*. If it's A and then B,
it is פיגול pigul *pigul*. So let's take a look. תנן התם
*Tnan hatam*. הרי זה תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים tmuras olah tmuras shelamim,
*Harei zeh tmurat olah tmurat shelamim*. So I go ahead and I
have an animal and I have an animal in front of me
and I said this animal should be an exchange for an עולה
olah *olah* and an exchange for שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*. So is it
an עולה olah שלמים shelamim. *olah shelamim* or did I first say
עולה olah *olah* and since the first words out of my mouth
were עולה olah *olah*, that got established its identity and the שלמים
shelamim. *shelamim* can't come and change it?
Or you can say it's חוזר בו *chozer bo*, can't I?
Well, yeah. Okay. הרי זו תמורת עולה דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Harei zu tmurat olah divrei Rabbi Meir*. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* says the first words establish it, the second words can't
change it. Okay. אמר amar, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, אם לכך נתכוון
תחילה הואיל ואי אפשר להוציא שתי שמות כאחת דבריו קיימין *Amar Rabbi
Yosi im l'kach nitkaven techila ho'il v'ee efshar l'hotzi shtei shemot k'achat
devarav kayamin*. If you really wanted to say that it was a
hybrid עולה שלמים shelamim. *olah shelamim*, since it's impossible to say both
words at one time, so that will go by what you intended
and we'll call it a hybrid. ואם משאמר הרי זו תמורת עולה
נמלך ואמר הרי זו תמורת שלמים הרי זו עולה *V'im mishe'amar harei
zu tmurat olah nimlach v'amar harei zu tmurat shelamim harei zu olah*.
But if what you did is you actually changed your mind, הרי
זו עולה *harei zu olah*, then it goes by the first thing.
So it's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* seems like he's saying
we can't have any rule, we have to decide what you were
trying to say and we'll look at what you're trying to say.
תוספות Tosafos's *Tosafot* within רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* tries to
say even within רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* we would look
about like maybe how long you paused. If you did תוך כדי
דיבור *toch kdei dibbur*, then we'll say you meant it all as
one thing. If you had a slightly longer pause, we'll look at
it as a reconsideration. Okay, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi*
anyway looks at certain contextual clues to decide whether you tried to
say it all at once or not. But it seems like for
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, even if we acknowledge that you
were trying to say it all at once, okay, nevertheless, since the
first words out of your mouth were תמורת עולה *tmurat olah*, that
established its identity. All right.
What does it mean if it's תמורת עולה *tmurat olah* and תמורת
שלמים *tmurat shelamim* at the same time?
That you have to then redeem it and you split the money
for how you use it. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. Now, okay, איבעיא להו *Ibay'a lehu*. Now, did I
skip a line? Yeah, no. הרי זו תמורת עולה דברי רבי מאיר...
Rabbi Meir, *Harei zu tmurat olah divrei Rabbi Meir...* Now, איבעיא להו
*Ibay'a lehu*. Now we ask the following question. הרי זו תמורת עולה
ושלמים tmuras olah v'shelamim, מהו mahu. *Harei zu tmurat olah u'shelamim mahu*?
Let's say you said this is a תמורת עולה *tmurat olah* and
a שלמים *shelamim*. So you didn't say and תמורת שלמים *tmurat shelamim*,
you said and a שלמים *shelamim*. What's the story? Or לחצות lachatzos.
מהו *Lachatzot mahu*? Now let's say you say לחצות lachatzos? *lachatzot*. Now
there's two very different readings of the word לחצות l'chatsos, *lachatzot*. רש"י
Rashi, *Rashi* reads the words that you say, I want to split
this between עולה *olah* and שלמים *shelamim*. So there's no question what
you're intending. Okay. The way תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says it is, you
said, I want this to be a תמורה tmura? *tmura* and שלמים
*shelamim* when it reaches חצות *chatzot*. Okay. Or at חצות *chatzot* I
want this to be an עולה *olah* and a שלמים *shelamim*. So
what you're doing is the effect is all happening at the same
second. So you can't say that there's a sequential ordering of which
your words take effect. So one way or the other, the way
your words are framed, or the way in which you framed when
it takes effect, it's clear that you want it to be both.
But you still said the word עולה *olah* before the word שלמים
*shelamim*. But there's no question from your words that you're trying to
create a package hybrid type of a thing. What's the story? אמר
אביי Abaye *Amar Abaye* says אביי Abaye, *Abaye*, בהא וודאי מודה רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir, *be'ha vadai modeh Rabbi Meir*. In this case, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* would certainly agree that since you even
packaged it together with your words as it were, that it's half
and half. רבא Rava אמר עדיין היא מחלוקת *Rava amar adayin hi
machloket*. And רבא Rava *Rava* says nope, I don't care how obvious
that is or whatever, since the word עולה *olah* comes first and
something presumably can't be both an עולה *olah* and a שלמים *shelamim*,
it's maybe part of it. So I am just going to apply
the עולה *olah* part first. Okay.
So now let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
tie this in. בהא וודאי מודה רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *be'ha vadai
modeh Rabbi Meir*... אמר רבא לאביי *Amar Rava l'Abaye*... Okay. So, now
let's see how the גמרא Gemara is going to tie this in.
Okay. בודאי מודה רבי מאיר. Bevada'i modei Rabbi Meir. אמר רבא לאביי
לדידך דאמרת בבודאי מודה רבי מאיר, Amar Rava l'Abaye l'didach d'amarta bahavada'i
modei Rabbi Meir, according to you that you say when you all
let's say have take effect at the same time, I'm going to
read it that way because it's easier to tie it into the
comparison. We'll read תוספות's Tosafot version. If you wanted it to take
effect all at the same time, definitely רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, agrees
that it's all packaged. הרי שחיטה, Harei shechita, now we're going to
assume that the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says like you go
by the first thing is parallel to the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
here that says you go by the first thing. Okay. So now
we're going to say like this. Okay, but one minute, הרי שחיטה,
harei shechita, assuming that this case is,
we're actually following אילפא, Ilfa, assuming that
this case
is all let's say during one act, during שחיטה, shechita, okay, הרי
שחיטה
דלכי לחצות תני ופליגי. harei shechita d'lechi lachatzos tani u'pligi. So this
is like לחצות. l'chatsos
Why is this like לחצות? l'chatsos Why does it sort of package
it all together? Well, you could say because it's during one act,
but nevertheless you first say one and then you say the next.
Okay. So what תוספות Tosafot explains it is, is that, okay, this
is going to be the question of if, if you know,
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. yeshna l'shechita m'tchila v'ad sof. Here's the
two סימנים. simanim. Here's the trachea and the esophagus.
Okay. And now comes your knife here. Okay. Should I make it
here?
A nice long knife.
There's the base. Okay. Comes your knife, okay, and you're starting to
cut through. Okay. So we're going to assume you have to cut
both סימנים. simanim. We're going to assume אין לשחיטה אלא לבסוף. ein
l'shechita ela l'basof. It all becomes a שחיטה shechita basically when you
cut the majority of the trachea. So when are you saying these
words? You can't all be saying them at the last millimeter of
the of the trachea. You're saying these words, at this point you're
saying, you know,
כזית למחר k'zayis l'machar as you're sort of cutting here, and then
when you're there you're saying כזית בחוץ, k'zayis bachutz and none of
them have taken effect yet because the שחיטה shechita hasn't been done.
And only when the שחיטה shechita is done do we now say
you had these thoughts during the שחיטה. shechita. Okay. If אין לשחיטה
אלא לבסוף, ein l'shechita ela l'basof, you view this as the מעשה
שחיטה, ma'aseh shechita, only that one moment. So the thoughts preceded it,
but they, they were meaningful, they took effect at that moment. So
at that moment that's like saying, I want this to all take
effect tomorrow. Okay. They all got packaged together in that last second.
And nevertheless, assuming, oh actually we're assuming like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan
not like אילפא, Ilfa, assuming like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that they
debate there, you see that even when it gets packaged together, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's like the thought of כזית למחר k'zayis
l'machar took effect first. Okay. So this is like לחצות תני, lachatzos
tani, and nevertheless רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, says I'm still going to
view the כזית למחר k'zayis l'machar as coming first according to רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that even if it's all during שחיטה, shechita, we,
you know, it's fixed as פיגול pigul. because כזית למחר k'zayis lemachar
came first.
וכי אי אפשר לצמצם? V'chi ee efshar l'tzamtzem? No. No, not here.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. הרי שחיטה דלכי לחצות
תני ופליגי, Harei shechita d'lechi lachatzos tani u'pligi, and they debate, meaning
רבי, Rabbi. you know, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, still says this idea
that it's like that came first. Okay. אמר ליה מי סברת אין
לשחיטה אלא לבסוף ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף ומשנתנו דאמר סימן ראשון
חוץ לזמנו וסימן שני חוץ למקומו.
Amar lei mee savarta ein l'shechita ela l'basof? Yeshna l'shechita
m'tchila v'ad sof, u'mishnatenu d'amar siman rishon chutz l'zmano v'siman sheni chutz
l'komo. Okay. No, it's not that that's the מעשה שחיטה. ma'aseh shechita.
It's that all of this is the מעשה שחיטה. ma'aseh shechita. It's
a process. All of that is the מעשה שחיטה. ma'aseh shechita. And
if all of that is the מעשה שחיטה, ma'aseh shechita, there was
this for part of the מעשה שחיטה ma'aseh shechita followed by, not
at the same time, that for the second part of the מעשה
שחיטה. ma'aseh shechita. And since they were clearly at separate times, we
don't view them as being packaged together. That's why רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda said it. But if you said I want it all to
take effect at midday, right, or something like that, or you were
explicit and you said half of it should be, you know, I
want to divide it between X and Y and you didn't just
do it in sequence, okay, then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree.
And the reason here that we say this takes effect first is
because they are not, they are in sequence, they're not packaged together.
It's not that they all come at the last moment. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. והרי קמיצה דכי לחצות תני,
V'harei kmitza d'chi lachatzos tani, one minute. How about the קמיצה? kmitza?
You take the act of the קמיצה kmitza and presumably there too
they have this debate of if you say חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zmano
and then you say חוץ למקומו. chutz l'komo. And why is that
לחצות תני? lachatzos tani? Because presumably there too the קמיצה kmitza is,
now I don't know why you can't have the same question about
like it takes a few seconds, you know, it's a process, right?
It's not like... מנחה, Mincha, you're doing like this. Okay. But we're
assuming that that also is like one moment in time. So even
if you're thinking, I mean you could ask the same question, ישנה
לקמיצה מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshna l'kmitza m'tchila v'ad sof, you know? But
somehow the גמרא Gemara assumes that even if I'm thinking חוץ למקומו
חוץ לזמנו חוץ למקומו, chutz l'komo chutz l'zmano chutz l'komo, you know,
the קמיצה kmitza is only considered to take effect at that moment
when I finish it. Okay. And then both of the thoughts are
off. present at that moment. They preceded it and then they're both
present. There's no sequence. You don't consider it as A came first
and B came second because it all happened at that last moment.
והרי קמיצה v’harei kmitza דלכי חטאת דמי d’lichi chatat dami ופליגי u'pligi
and they debate. So the גמרא Gemara says no, we're not talking
about the act of קמיצה. kmitza. If the act of קמיצה kmitza
was there, they wouldn't be debating. That would be like it all
happened at the same time. התם נמי hatam nami שהקטיר she’hiktir קומץ
מנחה komatz mincha חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano קומץ לבונה komatz levona חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. We're not talking about the act of קמיצה, kmitza,
we're talking about the offering up of the קמיצה. kmitza. So first
you offer the, by a normal מנחה, mincha, you have the handbreadth
of the flour and the oil whatever, and then you have the
frankincense. So that's why, one during שחיטה shechita and one during זריקה.
zrika. But if you had it all during that one moment, okay,
then that would be, according to the idea that ר' מאיר Rebbi
Meir doesn't disagree when it's all לחצות, lachtzos, then ר' יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda wouldn't disagree either. That would all be like it's mixed together.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: והרי קומץ דמנחת חוטא v’harei komatz
d'minchat chotei דליכא לבונה בהדיה. d'leka levona bahadei. How about the קומץ
komatz of a מנחת חוטא minchat chotei that there's no לבונה? levona?
ופליגי u'pligi and presumably they debate that case. There's no קטורת, ketoret,
excuse me, לבונה, levona, yeah, there's no לבונה. levona. So there's only
the handbreadth of the flour and they nevertheless they argue. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says: לא פליגי. lo
pligi. No. Who says they argue in that case? Meaning this debate
of ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda about the whatever stages was said by
a מנחה. mincha. It doesn't necessarily say by a מנחת חוטא. minchat
chotei. Maybe by a מנחת חוטא minchat chotei he would agree that
that's all considered to be one moment and it's all mixed together.
Okay. So no, the גמרא Gemara says: לא פליגי. lo pligi. אמר
רב אשי: amar Rav Ashi: אם תמצא לומר פליגי, im timtza lomar
pligi, if you were to say that even in that case they
debate, ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda said it's possible that first it's פיגול
pigul and then it's, and it can't change, even though there's no
two stages there, there's only one קומץ. komatz. פליגי בפסיעות. pligi bifsiot.
Here would be the example where they could argue during one עבודה
avoda. and there are two stages. During the taking of the קומץ,
komatz, there's only one stage. During the offering up of it, there's
only one stage. But during the walking of it, every step is
considered distinct. Now, by the way, that's a little bit unclear, sort
of תוספות Tosafot asks this. Why is it that when I'm doing
the קמיצה, kmitza, do we say that the thoughts I have during
this part are not considered sequential because the קמיצה kmitza is only
at that last second? And when I do the offering, it's only
at that last second, so any previous thoughts get bundled up together.
But when I do the walking, each thought is distinct. So תוספות
Tosafot says well like a walking, each, even though it's a process,
we can separately identify each step as a separate act. We don't
identify like you moved your hands a millimeter, a second millimeter, those
are not defined as separate acts. So therefore, by the walking, so
you first had that thought and then you had that thought.
Whereas if I'm doing it this
way, I don't say I first had thought when I bent my
fingers this way and then another thought when I bent my fingers
this way. We don't say אין שייך. en shayach. We just say
when you finish it, you've had both thoughts. Okay. תוספות says a
similar point about this, why don't we say, why do we say
you had thought one at this stage and thought two at this
stage? What if I had thought one as I was cutting through
one millimeter of this and thought two as I was cutting through
the other millimeter? תוספות says no, that's all the same time. In
order for us to define it as sequential, they have to be
discrete acts. Okay. So that's why the גמרא Gemara says, yes you
can have the debate by the מנחה mincha during one עבודה avoda
without separating it into two עבודות. avodot What would be the during
one עבודה? avoda. It would be one step and another step. Okay.
So, one more time. We're saying, if, assuming that ר' מאיר Rebbi
Meir would agree that when they would all get packaged together at
the end of a particular time, it's going to take effect then
or they came together prior during an act and they get packaged
together by the end of the act, that he would agree, ר'
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda could still disagree by one עבודה avodah if you
have discrete parts. This one thought here, one thought there. That's a
way he could disagree by one עבודה. avodah, One step one way,
the next step the other, or burning the קומץ komatz and burning
the לבונה. levona. Anytime you have two discrete sets by one עבודה
avodah he could disagree. But if there's only one discrete step, then
it could be that then it really does get packaged together. Okay.
Depending on how you explain on this debate of ר' מאיר. Rebbi
Meir. Yes. You said that would be the הלכה halacha for the
animals? Yeah, exactly. All the other ones would be like one. Right.
All of this is within ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that says ר'
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would say his position even within one עבודה. avodah
But now what we're saying is, assuming that you need to get
those thoughts discrete, right within this question within ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir
about if you said לחצות or whatever, then we'd have to find
scenarios in which they were discrete. Different steps, different סימנים simanim of
the בהמה behema and so on. Okay. רב שימי בר אשי Rav
Shimi bar Ashi מתני הכי matni hachi כהביי. ke'Abaye. רב שימי בר
אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi teaches like אביי Abaye that in the
case of לחצות ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir would agree, okay, and meaning
and we have to... Therefore, in order to get רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda here to work, we have to make them discrete steps. Okay.
רב הונא בר נתן מתני כדרבא. Rav Huna bar Nasan masni k'de
Rava. He teaches like רבא that even when it's לחצות, even when
you're trying to bundle them together, even there we consider that the
first statement comes first and, you know, and we don't bundle it
together. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי מאיר, Ki asa Rav Dimi
amar Rabbi Meir, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came he said in
the name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. אמר, when רב דימי Rav
Dimi came he said, רבי מאיר בשיטת רבי יהודה אמרה, Rabbi Meir
b'shittas Rabbi Yehuda amrah, דאמר תפוס לשון ראשון. d'amar tfos lashon rishon.
So רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir this is what we're sort of assuming,
what we've been assuming in our previous discussion, that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda you go by the first
thing, that establishes its identity, and the thing that says comes later
doesn't change its identity. Okay, now of course whatever, of course רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda you know, the Rabbis who argue on רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda might in general agree with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir They're
just saying that in our case of תמורה there's a separate הלכה
halacha of, you know, עד ש... ad she... what is it? כקרב
המתיר כמצותו, karev hamatir kemitzvaso, right? So, you know, they might just
say no, fine, it's established as a פיגול pigul, but there's a
separate הלכה halacha if you פסול pasul something else you ruin it.
I mean, you stop it from being a פיגול. pigul But within
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. within רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says that
once it's פיגול pigul it doesn't stop being פיגול, pigul, he says
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying... I got it wrong. החכמים
haChachamim of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda? could agree normally that once a
thing is established as A, if you have another thought it doesn't
stop it. And nevertheless they say by פיגול pigul. another thought ruins
it because there's a הלכה halacha of כקרב המתיר כמצותו. karev hamatir
kemitzvaso. Fine. But within רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda who says once it's
פיגול pigul it doesn't stop being פיגול, pigul okay, that idea clearly
follows רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that if you have two thoughts it's
defined by the first thought. Okay. So that you're ruining it from
פיגול. piggul Right, exactly. Okay. בשיטת רבי יהודה אמרה, b'shittas Rabbi Yehuda
amrah, דאמר תפוס לשון ראשון. d'amar tfos lashon rishon. דתנן אמר רבי
יהודה זה הכלל אם מחשבת הזמן קדמה למחשבת המקום פיגול וחייבין עליו
כרת. Detnan amar Rabbi Yehuda zeh haklal im machsheves hazman kodma l'machsheves
hamakom pigul v'chayavin alav kares. Fine. So that's the idea. Once it's
thought A, thought B doesn't come and change the status. Okay. אמר
ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, said אביי, Abaye. והא רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן כי מגסהו, veha Rabba bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan ki magis'hu, but one minute, you're saying, you know, within
this debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi
right, which is that what case of תמורה עולה תמורה שלמים, tmura
olah tmura shelamim, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda lines up with רבי מאיר.
Rebbi Meir But one minute, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan, says if you
actually try to, you know, try to bring them close, כי מגסהו
ki magis'hu רבי מאיר ורבי יוסי בהדי הדדי לא פליגי. Rabbi Meir
v'Rabbi Yossi bahadi hadadi lo peligi. If you try, you can bring
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי Rabbi יוסי really close to one
another and say that there's really not even a debate between רבי
Rabbi. מאיר and רבי Rabbi יוסי when they say תמורה עולה תמורה
שלמים. tmura olah tmura shelamim. So the גמרא Gemara says לא פליגי?
lo peligi? The גמרא Gemara, says ולא פליגי? v'lo peligi? והא מפלג
פליגי. Veha miflag peligi. What do you mean they don't debate? They
do debate. They're debating what happens if you say תמורה עולה תמורה
שלמים. tmura olah tmura shelamim. So אמר ליה פליגי במאי דפליגי ולא
פליגי במאי דלא פליגי. amar lei peligi bamai d'peligi v'lo peligi bamai
d'lo peligi. This is so tautological! Fine. Don't make it like a
bigger debate. Oh, there's some big fundamental debate of רבי Rabbi מאיר
and רבי Rebbi, יוסי and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is only going
like רבי מאיר. No, it's a very local debate. That's what it's
saying. They're debating the narrow thing they're debating. It's not some big
bigger logical debate of if you say A and then B, do
you go by A or do you do A and B? No,
no, it's this local debate. Okay, what's the local debate? So the
גמרא Gemara says, דאמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן הכל
מודים היכא דאמר תחול זו ואחר כך תחול זו דברי הכל לא
חלה. d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan hakol modim heicha
d'amar techol zo v'achar kach techol zo divrei hakol lo chaila. If
you say, you know, let first I want first it to be
an עולה and then I want it to be a שלמים, then
everybody agrees it's an עולה and not a שלמים. You've made it
very clear that you are sequential. לא תחול זו אלא אם כן
חלה זו, Lo techol zo ela im ken chala zo, I don't
want it to be an עולה until the moment when it also
becomes a שלמים. So in that case it's very clear you wanted
them both to happen at the same time, דברי הכל חלה. divrei
hakol chaila. Then they're both at the same time. כי פליגי דאמר
תמורה עולה תמורה שלמים. Ki peligi d'amar tmura olah tmura shelamim. The
only debate is when it wasn't clear from how you were saying
it what you were getting at. Did you mean first A and
then B or did you mean A and B at the same
time? Why don't you just ask him? Right, well that's part of
the question. רבי מאיר סבר, Rabbi Meir savar, מדיהוה ליה למימר תמורת
עולה ושלמים, midehava lei l'meimar tmura olah v'shelamim, since you could have
said 'ו', v', okay, ואמר תמורה עולה תמורה שלמים, v'amar tmura olah
tmura shelamim, שמע מינה הדר קא הדר ביה. shma mina hadar ka
hadar bei. That makes it clear that you then... that your second
thought was really a second thought. And then it's too late to
go back. And then it's too late to go back, right. ורבי
יוסי, v'Rabbi Yossi, and רבי יוסי would say, אי אמר תמורת עולה
ושלמים... i amar tmura olah v'shelamim... no, here's why he didn't say
it that way. Not because he wanted it to be first A
and then B. He wanted it to be A and... and be
at the same time. So why did he add the extra word
תמורה? Because he says הוה אמינא פלגא תמורת עולה פלגא תמורת שלמים,
hava amina palga tmurat olah palga tmurat shelamim, because in his mind
he thinks I can get this to be a hundred percent עולה
and a hundred percent שלמים. So he says to himself, I don't
want to say this is a תמורה עולה ושלמים tmura olah v'shelamim
because that would mean fifty-fifty. I don't want it to be fifty-fifty.
I want it to be a hundred-hundred. להכי אמר תמורת עולה תמורת
שלמים למימר דכולה עולה וכולה שלמים הויא. lehachi amar tmurat olah tmurat
shelamim lemeymar de-kula olah ve-kula shelamim havya. Now of course he's wrong,
it can't be a hundred-hundred either, but that's what he thinks. So
basically what we're saying here is two things. Number one is that
according to the debate of אביי Abaye, and רבא before with if
you said תמורת עולה ושלמים, tmuras olah v'shelamim. not תמורת עולה תמורת
שלמים, tmuras olah tmuras shelamim we're saying like אביי. Abaye We're saying
that in that case yes, רבי מאיר would agree that it's all
one package. Okay, it's all one. And because we're saying like אביי,
what we're doing is we're going further and we're saying and it's
not you know even within אביי he could have said is he
saying it a question of words or a question of intent? Here
we're making it very clear that what we really care about is
not some formal rule like Michael was saying, like some global thing
תפוס לשון ראשון tefos lashon rishon that we could then apply to
other cases. We're just trying to get to like unpack your words
and figure out what you're really getting at. Okay, which presumably would
mean we could use other contextual clues, maybe we could even ask
the guy, imagine something as radical as that. Okay. So, and because
that's what it's about ultimately is your intent, then it's not globalizable
to other cases, okay, where there might be a question of does
it first get defined as A and then as B and so
on. Okay, like if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י
Rashi. says like this, the the two the narrow first line of
רש"י. Rashi, במאי לא פליגי והא לא פליגי דקאמר הכא לא פליגי
בתפוס לשון ראשון be-mai lo peligi ve-ha lo peligi de-ka'amar hacha lo
peligi be-tefos lashon rishon אלא בדעתי דגברא בוכיח דיבורו על מחשבתו אבל
דרב אביי אית ליה דבתר כוונתו אזלינן. ella be-daati de-gavra bochiach diburo
al machshavto aval de-rav Abaye itlo de-basar kavanato azlinan. All agrees that
it's at the end of the day a question about what you
were intending. Okay, now would that mean here too it's a question
of what you were intending? Well, maybe not. Here there's more of
a question about once you have one thought out, maybe this establishes
its identity and so on. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. So don't take that debate of intent relevant to
other questions. אמר ליה, amar lei, so anyway, so this was the
question, how could you connect רבי מאיר to רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda,
Didn't רבה בר בר חנה Reb Bar Chanah bar Chanah say in
the name of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan, that that whole debate was
just a debate of intent, not a more formalistic debate that could
be applied elsewhere? אמר ליה, amar lei, הוא אמר לא פליגי, hu
amar lo peligi, so he says רבי מאיר and רבי יוסי don't
really have a big debate, it's just an unpacking what you're thinking
debate, ואנא אמינא פליגי v'ana amina peligi and I say they do
debate. You gotta love this in the גמרא, Gemara right? The גמרא
Gemara says like going back earlier and the גמרא Gemara says oh
but one minute, don't they debate about the case of a מנחה,
mincha, a מנחת חוטא? minchas chotei? No, they don't debate the case
of a מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei. Oh if they debate the case
about a מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, this is what they're debating about.
Like, you know, oh these two תנאים Tannaim they don't debate. What
do you mean they don't debate? They do debate. Fine, they debate
what they debate but they don't debate what they don't. Oh he
says they don't debate, I say they do debate. Anyway, a lot
of words פליגי, peligi, there probably more words פליגי peligi in this
one דף daf than any other דף daf in ש"ס. Shas. Yeah,
they're debating about whether they're debating. Exactly. Okay. אמר עולא ואיתימא רבי
יאשיה. amar Ulla v'itayma Reb Yoshiya. עולא Ulla says and some say
רבי יאשיה Rebbi Yoshiya says, אפשר ידעי חברן בבלאי. efsher yadin chavran
Bavla'ei. Now, now that we're done with that, sort of linking the
רבי מאיר and the to the רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda question, תמורת
עולה תמורת שלמים, and also trying to figure out whether this debate
of this position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is even during one
עבודה avodah and two discrete stages of one עבודה, avodah right, because
now the way we might want to be saying it if we
want, right, it's dependent. But we might want to be saying it
even according to this that this is סימן אחד siman echad and
this is, you know, סימן שני, siman sheini, you know, or פסיעה
אחת, psia achas, you know, or פסיעה שני, psia sheini, anyway, okay,
so anyway, but you know that debate here, right, is that position
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that it gets established first as one
way only by two separate עבודות or even during one עבודה avodah.
and if it's during one עבודה avodah, maybe by two discrete stages.
That's point number one. Now we have another question, which is when
you said כזית kezayit and כזית kezayit here, this is a little
similar to the question about תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים versus תמורת עולה
ושלמים. Okay, when you said this, assuming I think we're pretty much
still assuming רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, one עבודה really only makes sense
if you're assuming רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, to the idea that this
is separate things and it gets established as פיגול piggul. according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, is that only when you said it כזית
k'zayis and then you said pause כזית? k'zayis What if you did
כזית וכזית? k'zayis v'k'zayis? Okay. So there you were during your שחיטה
shechita or during your פסיעה, psia, again we're assuming רבי יוחנן, כזית
בחוץ וכזית למחר. k'zayis bachutz v'k'zayis lemachar. So if you said כזית
k'zayis בחוץ bachutz, step one, כזית k'zayis? למחר lemachar step two, okay,
first it was פיגול piggul. for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? it doesn't
become something else. But if you say the ו, vav, but you
know, does that then say that then again it's... packaged and it
stopped being פיגול piggul. or no, even then it's separate. That's our
next question. כזית כזית תנן k'zayit k'zayit tnan or כזית וכזית תנן.
k'zayit vek'zayit tnan. Okay, אפשר דידעין חבריי בבלאי, Efshar deyad'in chavrei Bavlay,
is it possible that our friends our Babylonian friends know whether כזית
כזית תנן k'zayit k'zayit tnan or כזית וכזית תנן. k'zayit vek'zayit tnan.
Whether it's with the ו vav or without the ו. vav. It's
very interesting because you would think that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
they had a better tradition, right, since it's of the משנה Mishnah
of the original נוסח nusach of the משנה. Mishnah. So why did
they think their Babylonian friends know it? You know, maybe because they
figure out that a Babylonian friend, I mean, are in, you know,
are better in terms of the sort of, you know, it's true,
like whatever the נציב Netziv points out, that in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael they were more about מסורה mesorah and in general you see
that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi more cares about like sticking to the פשט
p'shat of the Mishnayic sources, whereas in the בבלי Bavli they were
more about their own like, you know, analysis, you know, and not
as wedded to the text. So maybe the point is like we
don't know the exact text, maybe they could sort of maybe they
figured it out through their analysis or something. Anyway, is it possible
that our Babylonian friends know whether the משנה Mishnah is כזית כזית
k'zayit k'zayit or כזית וכזית תנן? k'zayit vek'zayit tnan? כזית כזית תנן
או כזית וכזית אי הכי כל עירוב מחשבות הוי. K'zayit k'zayit tnan
o k'zayit vek'zayit ei hachi kol erev machshavot havei. If you added
the ו vav then even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree that
that makes it all one big thought and it's and it doesn't
get to be פיגול. pigul. או דילמא כזית וכזית תנן דרבי יהודה
פרטא הוי. O deilma k'zayit vek'zayit tnan deRabbi Yehuda prata havei. Even
when you say the ו, vav, for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda those
are discrete thoughts, that's what פרטא prata here means, וכל שכן כזית
כזית vechol sheken k'zayit k'zayit and certainly כזית k'zayit without the ו,
vav, you know, would be a discrete thought and it's already פיגול.
pigul תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here. דבעי מיניה לוי מרבי.
Debayei minei Levi meRabbi. לוי Levi asked from רבי. חישב לאכול כזית
למחר בחוץ מהו. Chishav leechol k'zayit lemachar bachutz mahu. According to רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda let's say the guy thought, I'm going to eat
one כזית k'zayit tomorrow for my picnic in Central Park. Okay, so
that's clearly עירוב מחשבות erev machshavot because it's the exact same thought
about what he's going to do with this כזית, k'zayit, he's thinking
both to do this one כזית k'zayit חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. But nevertheless the first thing he said was
tomorrow. What would be that for רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda Okay מהו.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, oh, זו שאלה. zo she'elah. That's a good
question. Okay, but עירוב מחשבות הוי, erev machshavot havei, at the end
of the day you're right, that's a case that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would agree that they're all mixed together and it does not
get to be פיגול. pigul, אמר לפניו רבי שמעון ברבי. Amar lifnei
Rabbi Shimon beRabbi. It's always fascinating רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי's son,
always seems to be like in competition with עולא. Ulla. Okay, one
also wonders was he competing for his father's affection or whatever. Anyway,
so he said to his father, he said, לא משנתינו היא? Lo
mishnateinu hi? What do you mean, ah what a brilliant question, you
know, wait a minute, it's clear in our משנה Mishnah that that
would be a case that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree. Why?
Because our משנה Mishnah says, לא משנתינו היא לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית
למחר כזית למחר כזית בחוץ כחצי כזית בחוץ כחצי כזית למחר כחצי
כזית למחר כחצי כזית בחוץ, lo mishnateinu hi leechol k'zayit bachutz k'zayit
lemachar k'zayit lemachar k'zayit bachutz k'chazi k'zayit bachutz k'chazi k'zayit lemachar k'chazi
k'zayit lemachar k'chazi k'zayit bachutz, all those cases פסול ואין בו כרת,
pasul ve'ein bo kareit, and on that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said,
no it goes by the first thought. So it's only when it's
one כזית k'zayit בחוץ bachutz and a different כזית k'zayit למחר lemachar
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you go by the first thought.
האידך Ha'idach the other case עירוב מחשבות הוי. erev machshavot havei. It
would all be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree that that would
be not one, you know, that they would all be mixed together.
So what are you doing praising, he never praised me, what are
you doing praising him, oh what a great question, it's clear from
our משנה. Mishnah. אמר ליה Amar lei now remember who authored the
משנה? Mishnah? רבי. He was the editor. So רבי said to him,
אמר ליה הוא שאל בי דבר חכמה. amar lei hu she'al bi
devar chochmah. He asked me a wise question meaning a logical question
meaning which can which which not based on text, just based on
סברא. svara. Okay, from a סברא svara point of view it's a
good question. Now ואתה אמרת משנתינו, ve'atah amarta mishnateinu, and you said
oh you ignored the fact that conceptually it's a good question, you
just said we can infer it from the משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה
Mishnah was talking about about a case of more discrete, obviously more
combined it would be agreed. Okay, לדידך דתניתך תרתי לא קשיא לך.
Ledidach dasnitach tarti lo kasha lach. The reason that for you you
were able to learn it from the משנה Mishnah and he wasn't
able to learn it from the משנה Mishnah was I was still
working out the text of the משנה, Mishnah, whatever I did in
versions of the text of the משנה, Mishnah, and your text was
different than his text. And that's why you could infer it and
he and he and he couldn't infer it. Now here's what the
גמרא's Gemara going to say, it's going to be a complicated. So
was there like what a משנה ראשונה Mishnah Rishonah or something? Yeah,
not really, it's just a question of the נוסח. nusach. Okay, so
the גמרא's Gemara going to be a little whatever, the גמרא's going
to say like this: רבי taught רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the following
two cases: כזית כזית k'zayit k'zayit and כזית וכזית. k'zayit vek'zayit. Okay,
now these are obviously more combined, and he said in both of
those cases רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagree. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
was able to say... Okay, both of those two cases רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* disagrees, but clearly if they're all bundled up
in the same כזית kezayis *kzayis*, right, if you told me he
disagrees here and he disagrees here, but you didn't say the other
case, presumably the other case where it's all the same כזית kezayis
*kzayis* he agrees. That's what רבי *Rebbe* says to רבי שמעון *Rebbe
Shimon*. That's why you figured it out. But here was the problem
with I'm just going to tell you this outside and then I'm
going to read inside because it's a hard text to read inside,
but whatever you just get a little lost. Here's the problem with
what happened with with עולא *Ulla*. Was עולא *Ulla*, right? Was עולא
*Ulla*, yes? Who was it? Was עולא *Ulla*? לוי Levi *Levi*, I'm
sorry, right. Okay לוי Levi *Levi*, here's the problem that happened with
לוי *Levi*, right עולא *Ulla* was whatever anyway. Here's the problem that
happened with לוי *Levi*. Okay, so this is the text that רבי
שמעון *Rebbe Shimon* got, but לוי *Levi* got the text כזית kezayis.
כזית kezayis *kzayis kzayis*. That was the only text that לוי *Levi*
got. Okay, but when לוי *Levi* went to the בית מדרש *beis
medrash*, he heard all the other students including רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*,
right that they were saying this text. So here's what לוי *Levi*'s
question was. Now either one you should say you could infer that
something more combined would not be everybody would agree. But here's what
לוי *Levi* thought to himself. He said one minute, this is the
text I got, this is the text that everybody in the בית
מדרש *beis medrash* is saying. So what happened? Did they on their
own? Is this the really only right text and they on their
own added these added this case? If this is the really the
right text, then anything more combined would be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rebbe Yehuda* would agree. Okay, but maybe he said no, maybe what
happened is is that this is the text רבי *Rebbe* taught me.
Okay, but רבי *Rebbe* didn't teach me both cases, right? When רבי
*Rebbe* taught the students in the בית מדרש *beis medrash* he said
not only do they disagree in this case, they even disagree in
this case, even when they're a little bit more combined. Ah, but
if he didn't teach me everything, he he didn't teach me the
case of more being combined here, then when he taught them maybe
he didn't teach them everything either? And if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rebbe Yehuda* and if therefore רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* disagrees
even when they're more combined here, maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe
Yehuda* disagrees even when they're totally combined in one כזית *kzayis*. You
get it? It's sort of like if I see that I'm not
getting the whole story because I'm only say here they disagree here,
I would have assumed here they agree. But in the when he
taught to the students he said even here they disagree. So I'm
not getting the whole story, maybe they're not getting the whole story?
And maybe even when it's one כזית *kzayis* they disagree. So that's
why עולא *Ulla* who only got I לוי *Levi*, excuse me, who
only got this text and heard students had this text, couldn't infer
from the text because he maybe was thinking that the text itself
is incomplete, okay? So let's take a look. They would still agree
if it's כזית *kzayis* למחר lamachar, בחוץ bachutz *lemachar bachutz*? They would
still disagree. No, no, not only do they disagree here, right, if
you just said they would have disagreed here, I would have inferred
that here they agree. But then I see that when he teaches
the students he says they even disagree in this case. So once
that's true, maybe there's also a third case they disagree. No, no,
but if he said כזית למחר בחוץ bachutz *kzayis lemachar bachutz*, then
they would all agree that it would be No, לוי *Levi* thinks
that maybe in that case they would also disagree. Ah, don't tell
me I should infer it since since רבי *Rebbe* didn't say it,
since it wasn't in this list, obviously they agree. Clearly רבי *Rebbe*
is not giving full So when do they agree? They never agree.
Alright, so that's why he had to ask me the question. Let's
take a look. Okay, and all of this by the way is
going to be a way to prove that in our משנה *Mishna*
we had כזית וכזית kezayis v'kezayis *kzayis v'kzayis* based on the fact
that לוי *Levi* got upset and רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*, you know
that רבי *Rebbe* whatever, that of this whole complaining of רבי שמעון
*Rebbe Shimon* to רבי *Rebbe*. Anyway, so let's take a look. Okay,
לדידי דאסני לי תרתי לא קשיא לך *L'didi d'asni li tarti lo
kashya lach*. לדידיה דלא אתנייה אלא חדא *L'didei d'lo asneiya ela chada*.
So I only taught him one. ושמעינהו לרבנן דקגרסי תרתי *V'sham'inhu l'rabanan
d'ka garsi tarti*. And he had the rabbis heard both versions. וסבר
דידי דוקא *V'savar didi davka*. So he didn't know. He said, is
mine the real text and anything more than this they agree? ודידהו
עירוב מחשבות *V'dideihu eiruv machshavos*, and in this case they really agree
and they just added that second case on their own and they're
wrong, רבי *Rebbe* is being very precise what he taught me, and
anything more than this would be עירוב מחשבות *eiruv machshavos*. או דילמא
דידהו דוקא *O dilma dideihu davka*. Or no, maybe רבי *Rebbe* was
taught them this text, that's רבי *Rebbe*'s text, not not their text.
And even that case is they disagree. And me he just gave
me an abbreviated list. ולדידי שיורי שייר לי *U'l'didi shiyuri shayer li*.
He gave me abbreviated list. אה בדי דשייר לי לדידי השייר להו
לדידהו נמי *Ah b'di d'shayer li l'didi hashyer l'hu l'dideihu nami*. So
maybe he gave them an abbreviated list. So maybe they don't only
disagree in this case, maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* would
have disagree even in the same כזית *kzayis*. Maybe we see רבי
*Rebbe* is giving abbreviated lists. Okay, so לדידהו נמי בהא *L'dideihu nami
beha*. Okay, so that's clear, that's how רבי *Rebbe* defended לוי *Levi*'s
question. לוי *Levi* has a good reason to ask the question because
he didn't know whether the lists are abbreviated or not abbreviated. Okay,
now the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to infer from this whether the גירסא
*girsa* is כזית כזית *kzayis kzayis* or כזית וכזית kezayis v'kezayis *kzayis
v'kzayis*. Okay, מאי אתנייה *Mai asneiya*? Now which text was taught to
לוי *Levi*? אילימא כזית וכזית אתנייה *Ilima kzayis v'kzayis asneiya*, if לוי
*Levi* had the כזית וכזית *kzayis v'kzayis* case, and then in the
בית מדרש *beis medrash* they had the כזית כזית כזית *kezayis kezayis*
case, then there's no abbreviated, right? Then לוי *Levi* at least got,
if they even disagree in this case, if this was the text
taught לוי *Levi*, implicitly he's being told that they disagree in the
כזית וכזית *kezayis ve'kezayis* case, right? If they disagree if this case
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* is considered they disagree, right רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*, then clearly they disagree this. So when
he hears them in the בית מדרש *beis medrash* saying this, that's
not at all different than the text that he received. Okay. You
guys with me here? Okay. So אילימא כזית וכזית אתניה *Ilei ma
kezayis u'kezayis asneih* היי לאו שיורא הוא *hai lav shiyura hu*, then
his text wasn't abbreviated. אלא כזית כזית אתניה *Ela kezayis kezayis asneih*.
So it must be that his text was כזית כזית *kezayis kezayis*.
Their text was כזית כזית *kezayis kezayis* and כזית וכזית *kezayis u'kezayis*.
His text was abbreviated because from his you could have inferred that
this case they agreed, and he found out no, even in this
case רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* disagrees and considers that separate.
So he says, if I'm getting an abbreviated text, maybe they're getting
an abbreviated text. Okay. Now the גמרא *Gemara*, so now we prove
that the text was though that the okay fine that כזית וכזית
*kezayis u'kezayis* at the end of the day was ultimately the text
of רבי *Rebbi* that even in the כזית וכזית *kezayis u'kezayis* case,
you know, they disagree. It's only in the case of one כזית
*kezayis* that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rebbi Yehuda* would say it's עירוב
מחשבות *eiruv machshavos*. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this:
וטיבעי ליה כזית וכזית *V'tibaei lei kezayis u'kezayis*. Now, here's לוי *Levi*.
He's got this text. He sees this. He doesn't know, did the
students add this or is this the or does רבי *Rebbi* agree
to this case? So why does he ask רבי *Rebbi* his case
of one כזית *kezayis*? Why not go straight to רבי *Rebbi* and
ask him this case? רבי *Rebbi*, I hear the students are saying
in your name are saying כזית וכזית *kezayis u'kezayis* there's a disagreement,
is that true? Do they also disagree in the case with the
ו vav, *vav*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, where were we, וטיבעי
ליה כזית וכזית *v'tibaei lei kezayis u'kezayis*. סבר איבעי מיניה חדא דלשמע
תרתי *Savah ibaei minei chada d'lishma tarti*. No, I'm going to ask
him רבי *Rebbi* the case of one כזית *kezayis*. Okay, so here's
לוי *Levi*. Okay, this is the text that he's got. And he
doesn't know two things. This is the text that the students have,
you're all the students, these are this is the text that they
have. So לוי *Levi*, he doesn't know if this is true. Maybe
that part is something the students added, and maybe in that case
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* agrees. And he also doesn't know
a more extreme case of one כזית *kezayis*. Okay. He also doesn't
know whether would רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agree in the one כזית
*kezayis*. Meaning this כזית *kezayis* למחר *l'machar* לחוץ לזמנו *l'chutz lizmano*? Right,
exactly. למחר *L'machar* and לחוץ למקומו *l'chutz limkomo*. Right, exactly. So, he
says, I'll ask רבי *Rebbi* this case and then I'll be able
to figure out both. Now, you'll only be able to figure out
both if he says this is a debate. If this is a
debate then this is a debate. But if this רבי יהודה *Rebbi
Yehuda* agrees, you don't know about that. So let's see how either
way you ask one question, you won't be able to figure out
both, it depends on the answer. Okay. So he says, let's take
a look. איבעי מיניה חדא דלשמע תרתי *Ibaei minei chada d'lishma tarti*.
דאי בעינא כזית וכזית *D'ei baeina kezayis u'kezayis*. If I just ask
him, hey, what's the story with this? Does רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*
agree in that or not? הניחא דאי אמר לי כללא *Ha nicha
d'ei amar li klala*. If he says to me in this case
רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agrees that it's עירוב מחשבות *eiruv machshavos*, that's
what the word כללא *klala* means, it's all one
big statement. In this
case רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agrees. כל שכן כזית למחר בחוץ *Kol
sheken kezayis l'machar bachutz*. And certainly רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* would say
this is all one big statement. Okay. אלא אי אמר לי פרטא
*Ela ei amar li prata*. But if he says no, in this
case רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* says they're separate. So then אכתי כזית
למחר בחוץ קמיבעיא לי *achti kezayis l'machar bachutz kamibaiya lei*. I won't
know the story about when it's all in one כזית *kezayis*. Okay,
so fine. אי הכי *Ei hachi*, says the גמרא *Gemara*, okay, but
same's true if you ask start with this. Depending on the answer
you're not going to know. אי הכי התם נמי *Ei hachi hatam
nami*. התנא דאי אמר ליה כזית למחר בחוץ פרטא *Hatna d'ei amar
lei kezayis l'machar bachutz prata*. If you say this case, even in
this case רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* would say it's separate statements and
it still remains פיגול pigul, *pigul*. כל שכן כזית וכזית *Kol sheken
kezayis u'kezayis*. Certainly the כזית וכזית *kezayis u'kezayis* case. אלא אי אמר
ליה כללא *Ela ei amar lei klala*. But if as what רבי
*Rebbi* did answer, he says no, in this case רבי יהודה *Rebbi
Yehuda* agrees, it's all one big statement. So אכתי כזית וכזית מיבעיא
ליה *achti kezayis u'kezayis mibaiya lei*, and לוי *Levi* still doesn't know
the story about the כזית וכזית *kezayis u'kezayis*, because that wasn't part
of לוי *Levi*'s text. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no. אם כן
*Im ken*, he can figure it out. You know how he'll figure
it out? Whether רבי *Rebbi* gets angry when רבי *Rebbi* answers or
not. Okay. Fascinating. אם כן מירתח רתח *Im ken mirtach rasach*. Okay.
Because if the story was that this רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agreed,
and רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agreed in this case by כזית וכזית
*kezayis ve'kezayis*. Then when I ask him, hey, what's the story of
it's all one כזית *kezayis*? He would have gotten angry. He would
have said, what a stupid question! What do you mean what כזית
*kezayis*? רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agrees even if it's כזית וכזית *kezayis
ve'kezayis*! Okay, so if he gives me says like he answer he
gave me, ah, that's a good question. That finally is a case
that רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agrees, then I know that this case
רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* disagrees. Okay. But if he says, if he
says what a stupid question, of course רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* agrees
there, how can you even ask I mean even in this case
רבי יהודה agrees, excuse me. Right. So he says, so then is
he, so if he said yes רבי יהודה agrees here, but he
said it in an angry way, so אם כן מירתחתא הא כזית
וכזית כללא? im kein mirtachtach ha kezayis v'kezayis k'lala? How can you
ask such a stupid question? Of course רבי יהודה agrees here, he
even agrees here! כזית למחר כזית חוץ מבעיא? kezayis l'machar kezayis chutz
mibaiya? So basically by asking this, I'll know both answers. If he
tells me רבי יהודה disagrees here, obviously he disagrees. If he tells
me רבי יהודה agrees, but he tells me nicely and says, oh
what a good question רבי יהודה agrees, I'll know that כזית וכזית
רבי יהודה you know disagrees. If he tells me רבי יהודה agrees
but it was obvious, then I'll know כזית וכזית also רבי יהודה
agrees. All right, wonderful. Now we have finally resolved our question and
if you look at רש"י, Rashi okay רש"י Rashi basically says, okay,
ובעין אפשיט, uvayan ifshit, right, three lines from... Right, three lines from
the top, ובעין אפשיט. uvayan ifshit. דבעינן להו כזית כזית תנן או
כזית וכזית תנן שמע מינה כזית וכזית תנן. d'be'inan leihu kezayis kezayis
t'nan o kezayis v'kezayis t'nan shma mina kezayis v'kezayis t'nan. At the
end of the day, this is the text that לוי got, this
is the text that the students got, but the text that the
students got was correct. לוי did get an abbreviated list. This is
the text: this case one כזית is actually רבי יהודה does agree,
that's all mixed up. But even with the ו, vav okay רבי
יהודה still disagrees. So assuming כאיפסו keipso רבי יהודה says the first
thing gets established, later thing doesn't ruin it, presumably like רבי יוחנן,
even if it's all during one עבודה and even if there's a
ו vav to connect it, the first thing takes effect and it
can already become פיגול. pigul, The only way it wouldn't be פיגול
pigul, is if you thought about one כזית to do both בחוץ
and למחר, or if you thought the בחוץ thought first. Okay. And
then רש"י just ends by saying ומהכא אמרינן בגמרא דאמר לחבירו בקידושין
ובגמרא דשבועת הפקדון רבי היא דאמר לא שנא כזית כזית לא שנא
כזית וכזית פרטא הוי. umeihacha amrinan b'gemara d'amar lachaveiro b'kiddushin u'bgemara d'shvua'at
hapikadon Rebbi hi d'amar lo shna kezayis kezayis lo shna kezayis v'kezayis
perata havei. So in other places in ש"ס, Shas, the גמרא wants
to know about when you have two statements, does the ו vav
make it one statement? And it refers back to this גמרא that
based on what we just figured out, that within רבי, you're right,
even within רבי יהודה where רבי יהודה says that if it's one
statement you go by the first, okay, and it's only if it's
all together does it prevent it from being פיגול, pigul. okay, so
that even the ו vav doesn't make it together. The only thing
that would make it together would be if you said that it's
all about the same כזית. Okay, but if you said it's about
different כזיתים, kezeisim, the ו does not do enough to make it
all together. Bottom line is that according to the חכמים, chachamim, even
once you've made it פיגול, pigul, if you do something later wrong,
it stops being פיגול, pigul? even at a completely later עבודה. According
to רבי יהודה, once it's established as פיגול, pigul. if it starts
being something else wrong, it doesn't become פיגול. Once it's established as
פיגול, it doesn't stop, and the only question is: when can you
make that other thought so much packaged together that it never got
to be פיגול? Okay, and if you said at the same כזית
maybe you would do it. Okay, but the same עבודה, different כזיתים
kezeisim or whatever, that's already separate, and therefore רבי יהודה it doesn't
stop being פיגול.